<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc docName='draft-irtf-pearg-safe-internet-measurement-08' ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IRTF" category="info" xml:lang="en"><!-- xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"-->
<front>

<title abbrev='Safe Internet Measurement'>
Guidelines for Performing Safe Measurement on the Internet
</title>

<author initials="I. R." surname="Learmonth" fullname="Iain R. Learmonth">
  <organization>HamBSD</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street></street>
    </postal>
    <email>irl@hambsd.org</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials="G." surname="Grover" fullname="Gurshabad Grover">
  <organization>Centre for Internet and Society</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street></street>
    </postal>
    <email>gurshabad@cis-india.org</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials="M." surname="Knodel" fullname="Mallory Knodel">
  <organization>Center for Democracy and Technology</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street></street>
    </postal>
    <email>mknodel@cdt.org</email>
  </address>
</author>

<date />

<area></area>
<workgroup></workgroup>
<keyword>safety</keyword>
<keyword>measurement</keyword>
<keyword>monitoring</keyword>
<keyword>research</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>Internet measurement is important to researchers from industry, academia and civil society. While measurement of the internet can give insight into the
functioning and usage of the internet, it can present risks to user privacy and safety.
This document describes briefly those risks and proposes guidelines for ensuring that internet measurements can
be carried out safely, with examples.</t>
</abstract>

<note title="Note">
<t>This document is a draft. It is not an IETF product. It does not propose a standard. Comments are solicited and should be addressed to the research group's mailing list at pearg@irtf.org and/or the author(s).</t>
<t>The sources for this draft are at:</t>
<t>https://github.com/IRTF-PEARG/draft-safe-internet-measurement</t>
</note>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>Measurement of the internet provides important insights and is a growing area of research. Similarly,
the internet plays a role in enhancing research methods of different kinds.</t>
<t>Performing research using the internet, as opposed to an isolated testbed
or simulation platform, means that experiments co-exist in a space with other
services and end users. Furthermore privacy considerations are of particular importance in internet measurement research that depends on collaboration and data sharing models between industry and academia<xref target="CAIDA"></xref>.</t>
<t>This document outlines guidelines for academic, industry and civil society researchers
who might use the internet as part of scientific experimentation to mitigate
risks to the safety of users.</t>

<section anchor="scope" title="Scope of this document">
<t>These are guidelines for how to measure the internet safely.
  When performing research on a platform shared with live traffic from other users,
  that research is considered safe if and only if other users are protected from or unlikely to experience danger,
  risk, or injury arising due to the research, now or in the future.</t>

<t>Following the guidelines contained within this document is not a substitute for institutional ethics review processes, although these guidelines
could help to inform that process. It is particularly important for the growing area of research that includes internet measurement to better equip review boards to evaluate internet measurement methods <xref target="SIGCOMM"></xref>, and we hope that this document is part of that larger effort.</t>
 
<t>Similarly, these guidelines are not legal
advice and local laws must also be considered before starting any experiment
that could have adverse impacts on user safety.</t>

<t>The scope of this document is restricted to guidelines that mitigate exposure
to risks to user safety when measuring properties of the internet:
the network, its constituent hosts and links, or user traffic.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
<t>Threat model: A threat is a potential for a security violation, which exists when
there is a circumstance, capability, action, or event that could
breach security and cause harm <xref target="RFC4949"></xref>.</t>

<t>User: For the purpose of this document, an internet user is an individual or
  organisation whose data is used in communications over the internet, most broadly, and those who use the internet to communicate or maintain internet
  infrastructure.</t>

<t>Active measurement: Active measurements generate
or modify traffic.</t>

<t>Passive measurement: Passive measurements involve the observation of existing traffic without active intervention.</t>

<t>On/off-path: A measurement that is on-path happens on the network. Off-path indicates activity in a side-channel, end-point or at other points where the user, their connection, or their data can be accessed.</t>

<t>One-/two-ended: A single-ended measurement is like a probe or a trace, whereas a measurement with two-ended control provides more accuracy but requires the cooperation of both endpoints, which might include the network itself if that is the measurement target.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="user-impact" title="User impact from measurement studies">
<t>Any conceivable internet measurement study might have an impact on an internet user's safety. 
The measurement of generated traffic may also lead to insights into other users'
traffic indirectly as well. It is always necessary to consider the best
approach to mitigate the impact of measurements, and to balance the risks of
measurements against the benefits to impacted users.</t>

<t>Some possible ways in which users can be affected as a result of an internet measurement study:</t>

<t>Breach of privacy: User privacy can be violated in the context of data collection. This impact also covers the case of an internet user's data
  being shared beyond that for which a user had given consent. First-order data that distinguishes a person such as name, as well as second-order data that can be used to track behaviour such as IP address, should be considered<xref target="Kenneally"></xref></t>

<t>Inadequate data protection: A scenario where data, either in
  transit or at rest, lacks sufficient protection from disclosure.
  Failure to meet user expectations for data protection is a concern,
  even if it does not result in unauthorized access to the data. This includes cases of improper access control
(i.e. people having access to user data who do not need it).</t>

<t>Traffic generation: A scenario where undue traffic is generated to traverse the
internet.</t>

<t>Traffic modification: A scenario where users' on-path internet traffic is nonconsensually modified.</t>

<t>Impersonation: A scenario where a user is impersonated during a measurement.</t>

<t>Legal: Users and service providers are bound by a wide range of policies from Terms of Service to rule of law, each according to context and jurisdiction. 
  A measurement study may violate these policies, and the consequences of such a violation may be severe.</t>

<t>Unavailability: Users or other entities may rely on the information or systems that are involved in the research and they may be harmed by unexpected or planned unavailability of that information or systems<xref target="Menlo"></xref>.</t>

<t>System or data corruption: A scenario where generated or modified traffic causes the
corruption of a system. This covers cases where a user's data may be
lost or corrupted, and cases where a user's access to a system may be affected as a result.
</t>

<t>Emotional trauma: A scenario where a measurement of or exposure to content or behaviour in an internet measurement study causes a user emotional or psychological harm.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="guidelines" title="Guidelines">
<section anchor="attribute" title="Attribute">
<t>Proactively identify your measurement to others on the network. "This allows any party or organization to understand what an unsolicited probe packet is, what its purpose is, and, most importantly, who to contact."<xref target="RFC9511"></xref> </t>
<t>Example: For a layer 3 IP packet probe you could mark measurements with a probe description URI as defined in RFC9511.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="consent" title="Obtain consent">
<t>Accountability and transparency are fundamentally related to consent. As per the Menlo Report, "Accountability demands that research methodology, ethical evaluations, data collected, and
results generated should be documented and made available responsibly in accordance with
  balancing risks and benefits."<xref target="Menlo"></xref> A user is best placed to balance the risks and benefits for themselves therefore consent must be obtained. From most transparent to least, there are a few options for obtaining consent.</t>

<section anchor="informed-consent" title="Informed consent">
<t>Informed consent should be collected from all users that
may be placed at risk by an experiment.</t>

<t>For consent to be informed, a reasonable coverage of possible risks must be presented to the users.
The considerations in this document can be used to provide a starting point
although other risks may be present depending on the nature of the measurements
to be performed. In addition, it should be clear from the consent language who the asker is, and what the terms
of data observation and/or collection are.</t>

<t>Example: A researcher would like to use volunteer-owned mobile devices to collect
information about local internet censorship. Connections will be attempted by the
volunteer's device with services and content known or suspected to be subject to censorship orders.</t>

<t>This experiment can carry substantial risk for the user depending on their specific
circumstances. Trying to access censored material can be seen as (network) policy infringement or breaking laws.
Consequences can range from disciplinary action from their employer to arrest or
imprisonment by government authorities. If the experimenter wants to expose volunteers to this kind of risk,
users must be fully informed, and voluntarily give consent to run the measurement.
Even then, experimenters should seriously consider designing their experiment in another way.</t>

<t>Note that informed consent is notoriously tricky to obtain. Conveying all possible risks of a measurement
  is often simply impractical, depending upon how technical the user audience is, the context of the consent prompt,
  what the tool is normally used by users for, etc. In addition, consent can have network effects. For example, asking a user
  to consent to sharing information about their communication with others can have
  impacts on users who have not personally consented to the study.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="proxy-consent" title="Proxy consent">
<t>In cases where it is not practical to collect informed consent from all
users of a shared network, it may be possible to obtain proxy consent. Proxy
consent may be given by a network operator or employer that would be more
familiar with the expectations of users of a network than the researcher.</t>
<t>In some cases, a network operator or employer may have terms of service that
specifically allow for giving consent to third parties to perform certain
experiments.</t>

<t>Example: Some researchers would like to perform a packet capture to determine the TCP
options and their values used by all client devices on a corporate wireless
network.</t>

<t>The employer may already have terms of service laid out that allow them to
provide proxy consent for this experiment on behalf of the employees, in this case the users
of the network. The purpose of the experiment may affect whether or not they
are able to provide this consent. Say, performing engineering work on
the network may be allowed, whereas academic research may not be
already covered.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="low-risk" title="Implied consent">
<t>In larger scale measurements, even proxy consent collection may not be
practical. In this case, implied consent may be presumed from users for some
measurements. Consider that users of a network will
have certain expectations of privacy and those expectations may not align with
the privacy guarantees offered by the technologies they are using. As a thought
experiment, consider how users might respond if asked for their informed
consent for the measurements you'd like to perform.</t>

<t>Implied consent should not be considered sufficient for any experiment that
may collect sensitive or personally identifying information. If practical,
attempt to obtain informed consent or proxy consent from a sample of users to
better understand the expectations of other users.</t>

<t>Example: A researcher would like to run a measurement campaign to determine the
maximum supported TLS version on popular web servers.</t>

<t>The operator of a web server that is exposed to the internet
hosting a popular website would have the expectation that it may be included in
surveys that look at supported protocols or extensions but would not expect that
attempts be made to degrade the service with large numbers of simultaneous
connections.</t>

<t>Example: A researcher would like to perform A/B testing for protocol feature and how
it affects web performance. They have created two versions of their software
and have instrumented both to report telemetry back. These updates will be
pushed to users at random by the software's auto-update framework. The telemetry
consists only of performance metrics and does not contain any personally
identifying or sensitive information.</t>

<t>As users expect to receive automatic updates, the effect of changing the
behaviour of the software is already expected by the user. If users have
already been informed that data will be reported back to the developers of the
software, then again the addition of new metrics would be expected. Note that
the reduced impact of A/B testing should not be used be an excuse to push updates that
might compromise user expectations around security and privacy.</t>

<t>In the event that something does go wrong with the update, it should be easy
for users to discover that they have been part of an experiment and roll back
the change, allowing for explicit refusal of consent to override the presumed
implied consent.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="share" title="Share responsibly">
<t>Further to use of measurement data, data is often shared with other researchers. Measurement data sharing comes with its own set of expectations and responsibilities of the provider.
Likewise there are responsibilities that come with the use of others’ measurement data. One obvious expectation is around end-user consent (see "Implied consent" above). <xref target="allman">Allman and Paxson</xref> provide "a set of guidelines that aim to aid the process of sharing measurement data... [in] a framework under which providers and users can
better attain a mutual understanding about how to treat particular
datasets."</t>
<t>Their guidance since 2007 has been for data providers to:</t>
<ul><li>explicitly indications of the terms of a dataset’s acceptable use</li>
<li>convey what interactions they desire or will accommodate.</li></ul>
<t>Their guidance for researchers is to:</t>
<ul><li>be thoughtful in the reporting of potentially sensitive information gleaned from providers’ data.</li>
<li>comply with the indications and interactions of the data providers.</li></ul>
<t>Example: Researchers have obtained network measurement data from more than one provider for purposes of conducting analysis of protocol use on both. Where privacy paritioning techniques are used, the researchers' findings may inadvertently collude to uncover private information about users. Once realised, researchers should mitigate this privacy risk to end users as well as disclosing this result to the data providers themselves.</t>
</section>
  
<section anchor="use-a-testbed" title="Isolate risk with a dedicated testbed">
<t>Wherever possible, use a testbed. An isolated network means that there are no
other users sharing the infrastructure you are using for your experiments.</t>
<t>When measuring performance, competing traffic can have negative effects on
the performance of your test traffic and so the testbed approach can also
produce more accurate and repeatable results than experiments using the public
internet.</t>

<t>Example: WAN link conditions can be emulated through artificial delays and/or packet
loss using a tool like <xref target="netem"></xref>. Competing traffic can
also be emulated using traffic generators.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="others-stuff" title="Be respectful of others' infrastructure">
<t>If your experiment is designed to trigger a response from infrastructure that
is not your own, consider what the negative consequences of that may be. At the
very least your experiment will consume bandwidth that may have to be paid for.</t>

<t>In more extreme circumstances, you could cause traffic to be generated that
causes legal trouble for the owner of that infrastructure. The internet is a
global network that crosses many legal jurisdictions and so what may be legal for
one is not necessarily legal for another.</t>

<t>If you are sending a lot of traffic quickly, or otherwise generally deviating
from typical client behaviour, a network may identify this as an attack which
means that you will not be collecting results that are representative of what
a typical client would see.</t>

<t>One possible way to mitigate this risk is transparency, i.e. mark measurement-related
  data or activity as such. For example, the popular internet measurement tool ZMap
  hardcodes its packets to have IP ID 54321 in order to allow identification
  <xref target="ZMap"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="do-not-scan" title='Maintain a "Do Not Scan" list'>
<t>When performing active measurements on a shared network, maintain a list of
hosts that you will never scan regardless of whether they appear in your target
lists. When developing tools for performing active measurement, or traffic
generation for use in a larger measurement system, ensure that the tool will
support the use of a "Do Not Scan" list.</t>

<t>If complaints are made that request you do not generate traffic towards a
host or network, you must add that host or network to your "Do Not Scan" list,
even if no explanation is given or the request is automated.</t>

<t>You may ask the requester for their reasoning if it would be useful to your
experiment. This can also be an opportunity to explain your research and offer
to share any results that may be of interest. If you plan to share the reasoning
when publishing your measurement results, e.g. in an academic paper, you must
seek consent for this from the requester.</t>

<t>Be aware that in publishing your measurement results, it may be possible to
infer your "Do Not Scan" list from those results. For example, if you measured a
well-known list of popular websites then it would be possible to correlate the
results with that list to determine which are missing. This inference might leak the fact
that those websites specifically requested to not be scanned.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="minimization" title="Minimize data">
<t>When collecting, using, disclosing, and storing data from a measurement, use
only the minimal data necessary to perform a task. Reducing the amount of data
reduces the amount of data that can be misused or leaked.</t>

<t>When deciding on the data to collect, assume that any data collected might
be disclosed. There are many ways that this could happen, through operational
security mistakes or compulsion by a judicial system.</t>

<t>When directly instrumenting a protocol to provide metrics to a passive
observer, see section 6.1 of RFC6973<xref target="RFC6973"></xref> for the data
minimization considerations enumerated below that are specific to the use case.</t>

<section anchor="minimization-discard" title="Discard data">
<t>Discard data that is not required to perform the task.</t>

<t>When performing active measurements, be sure to only capture traffic that you
have generated. Traffic may be identified by IP ranges or by some token that is
unlikely to be used by other users.</t>

<t>Again, this can help to improve the accuracy and repeatability of your
experiment. For performance benchmarking, <xref target="RFC2544"></xref>
requires that any frames received that were not part of the test traffic are
discarded and not counted in the results.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="minimization-mask" title="Mask data">
<t>Mask data that is not required to perform the task. This technique is particularly useful
for content of traffic to indicate that either a particular class of content
existed or did not exist, or the length of the content, but not recording the
content itself. The content can be replaced with tokens or encrypted.</t>

<t>It is important to note that masking data does not necessarily anonymize it
  <xref target="SurveyNetworkTrafficAnonymisationTech"/>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="minimization-aggregation" title="Aggregate data">
<t>When collecting data, consider if the granularity can be limited by using
bins or adding noise. Differential privacy techniques <xref target="DifferentialPrivacy"/> can help with this.</t>

<t>Example: <xref target="Tor.2017-04-001"></xref> presents a case-study on the in-memory
statistics in the software used by the Tor network.</t>
</section>
  </section>

<section anchor="minimization-generalize" title="Reduce accuracy">
<t>There are various techniques that can be used to reduce the accuracy of the collected data and make it
  less identifying.
</t>
<t>TODO: expand. Binning, categorizing, geoip, noise.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="risk-analysis" title="Analyze risk">
<t>The benefits of internet measurement should outweigh the risks.
Consider auxiliary data (e.g. third-party data sets) when assessing the risks. Consider that while a privacy risk may not be immediately apparent or realisable, in the future increased computing power may then make something possible.</t>
<t>Example: A research project releases encrypted payloads as a method for minimising exposure of sensitive user data. However the encryption could be trivially broken in the future with typical increases in computing power.</t>
</section>
</section> 

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>This document as a whole addresses user safety considerations for internet measurement studies, and thus discusses
  security considerations extensively throughout regarding collection and storage of user data.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>Many of these considerations are based on those from the
<xref target="TorSafetyBoard"></xref> adapted and generalised to be applied to
internet research.</t>

<t>Other considerations are taken from the Menlo Report
<xref target="Menlo"></xref> and its companion document
<xref target="MenloReportCompanion"></xref>.</t>

<t>Comments of several people on the mailing list was helpful, especially
Marwan Fayed and Jeroen van der Ham.</t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>
<references title="Informative References">
<reference anchor='netem'>
<front>
<title>Network emulation with NetEm</title>
<author initials='H.' surname='Stephen' fullname='S. Hemminger'><organization>Open Source Development Lab</organization></author>
<date year='2005' month='April'/>
</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor='RFC2544' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2544'>
<front>
<title>Benchmarking Methodology for Network Interconnect Devices</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='McQuaid' fullname='J. McQuaid'><organization /></author>
<date year='1999' month='March' />
<abstract><t>This document is a republication of RFC 1944 correcting the values for the IP addresses which were assigned to be used as the default addresses for networking test equipment. This memo provides information for the internet community.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2544'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2544'/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="TorSafetyBoard" target="https://research.torproject.org/safetyboard/">
<front>
<title>Tor Research Safety Board</title>
<author><organization>Tor Project</organization></author>
<date/>
</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor='RFC4949' target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4949">
<front>
<title>Internet Security Glossary, Version 2</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Shirey' fullname='R. Shirey'></author>
<date year='2007' month='August'/>
</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="Tor.2017-04-001" target="https://research.torproject.org/techreports/privacy-in-memory-2017-04-28.pdf">
<front>
<title>Privacy analysis of Tor's in-memory statistics</title>
<author initials="K." surname="Herm" fullname="K. Herm"><organization>Tor Project</organization></author>
<date year="2017" month="April" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Tor Tech Report" value="2017-04-001"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="Menlo" target="https://www.dhs.gov/sites/default/files/publications/CSD-MenloPrinciplesCORE-20120803_1.pdf">
<front>
<title>The Menlo Report: Ethical Principles Guiding Information and Communication Technology Research</title>
<author initials="D." surname="Dittrich" fullname="D. Dittrich"><organization/></author>
<author initials="E." surname="Kenneally" fullname="E. Kenneally"><organization/></author>
<date year="2012" month="August"/>
</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="MenloReportCompanion" target="https://www.impactcybertrust.org/link_docs/Menlo-Report-Companion.pdf">
<front>
<title>Applying Ethical Principles to Information and Communication Technology Research</title>
<author initials="M." surname="Bailey" fullname="M. Bailey"><organization/></author>
<author initials="D." surname="Dittrich" fullname="D. Dittrich"><organization/></author>
<author initials="E." surname="Kenneally" fullname="E. Kenneally"><organization/></author>
<date year="2013" month="October"/>
</front>
</reference>
<!-- Reference for differential privacy -->
<reference anchor="DifferentialPrivacy" target="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/11681878_14">
  <front>
  <title>Calibrating Noise to Sensitivity in Private Data Analysis</title>
  <author initials="C." surname="Dwork"><organization/></author>
  <author initials="F." surname="McSherry"><organization/></author>
  <author initials="K." surname="Nissim"><organization/></author>
  <author initials="A." surname="Smith"><organization/></author>
  <date year="2006"/>
  </front>
  </reference>
<!-- Reference for data masking != anonymization -->
<reference anchor="SurveyNetworkTrafficAnonymisationTech" target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3182660">
  <front>
  <title>A Survey of Network Traffic Anonymisation Techniques and Implementations</title>
  <author initials="N." surname="Van Dijkhuizen" fullname="Niels Van Dijkhuizen"><organization/></author>
  <author initials="J." surname="Van Der Ham" fullname="Jeroen Van Der Ham"><organization/></author>
  <date year="2018" month="May"/>
  </front>
</reference>
<!-- Reference for ZMap -->
<reference anchor="ZMap" target="https://github.com/zmap/zmap/blob/main/src/probe_modules/packet.c">
  <front>
  <title>ZMap Source Code - packet.c</title>
  <author><organization>University of Michigan</organization></author>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="RFC6973" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6937">
<front>
<title>Privacy Considerations for Internet Protocols</title>
<author initials="A." surname="Cooper" fullname="A. Cooper"><organization>CDT</organization></author>
<author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="H. Tschofenig"><organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization></author>
<author initials="B." surname="Aboba" fullname="B. Aboba"><organization>Skype</organization></author>
<author initials="J." surname="Peterson" fullname="J. Peterson"><organization>NeuStar, Inc.</organization></author>
<author initials="J." surname="Morris" fullname="J. Morris"><organization/></author>
<author initials="M." surname="Hansen" fullname="M. Hansen"><organization>ULD</organization></author>
<author initials="R." surname="Smith" fullname="R. Smith"><organization>Janet</organization></author>
<date year="2013" month="July"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6973'/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="SIGCOMM" target="http://conferences.sigcomm.org/sigcomm/2015/pdf/papers/nsethics/p17.pdf">
<front>
<title>Ethical Concerns for Censorship Measurement</title>
<author initials="B." surname="Jones" fullname="Ben Jones"><organization></organization></author>
<author initials="R." surname="Ensafi" fullname="Roya Ensafi"><organization></organization></author>
<author initials="N." surname="Feamster" fullname="Nick Feamster"><organization></organization></author>
<author initials="V." surname="Paxson" fullname="Vern Paxson"><organization></organization></author>
<author initials="N." surname="Weaver" fullname="Nick Weaver"><organization></organization></author>
<date year="2015" month="August"/>
</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor='RFC9511' target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9511">
<front>
<title>Attribution of Internet Probes</title>
<author initials='É.' surname='Vyncke' fullname='É. Vyncke'></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Donnet' fullname='B. Donnet'></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Iurman' fullname='J. Iurman'></author>
<date year='2023' month='November'/>
</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor='Allman' target="https://conferences.sigcomm.org/imc/2007/papers/imc80.pdf">
<front>
<title>Issues and Etiquette Concerning Use of Shared Measurement Data</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Allman' fullname='Mark Allman'></author>
<author initials='V.' surname='Paxson' fullname='Vern Paxson'></author>
<date year='2007' month='October'/>
</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor='caida' target="https://www.caida.org/catalog/datasets/sharing">
<front>
<title>Promotion of Data Sharing</title>
<author><organization>CAIDA</organization></author>
<date year='2010' month='January'/>
</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor='Kenneally' target="https://www.caida.org/catalog/papers/2010_dialing_privacy_utility/dialing_privacy_utility.pdf">
<front>
<title>Dialing privacy and utility: a proposed data-sharing framework to advance Internet research</title>
<author initials='E.' surname='Kenneally' fullname='Erin Kenneally'></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Claffy' fullname='Kimberly Claffy'></author>
<date year='2010'/>
</front>
</reference>
</references>

</back>

</rfc>
